Guide to the Wyckoff House papers 2020.004
Brooklyn Historical Society
Wyckoff House papers
1670-1935
1750-1870
Brooklyn Historical Society
Wyckoff House & Association
Wyckoff family
2020.004
3.88 Linear Feet in 1 half legal manuscript box, 2 oversize boxes, and 2 flat file folders.
The Wyckoff House papers is an assembled collection comprised of documents created by members and descendants of the Wyckoff family and by other families who lived in and around Brooklyn during the Dutch colonial period, Revolutionary War, and Civil War eras as well as documents that refer to the Pieter Claesen Wyckoff House. The material in the collection dates from 1670 to 1935 with the bulk of the documents spanning from 1750 to 1870. The content of the documents records transactional dealings, correspondence between members of the Wyckoff family, notes about the Wyckoff family tree, and is comprised of enslaved people indentures and bills-of-sale, deeds, correspondence, bonds, certificates, wills, maps, receipts, and lists.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to users without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred by the Wyckoff House Museum in 2020. The accession number associated with this transfer is 2020.004.
Existence and Location of Copies
Portions of this collection have been digitized. Please consult library staff for questions about access.
Arrangement
Due to the assembled nature of this collection, lack of recognizable original order, and donor supplied item-level inventory, materials in this collection are arranged by document type groupings. The arrangement of the collection reflects the groupings by document type from WHA's inventory. The arrangement is as follows:
Series 1: Legal and Transactional Documents, 1687-1917
Series 2: Correspondence and General Documents, 1670-1888, undated
Series 3: Maps, 1935
Biographical / Historical
The Wyckoff family was a Dutch family that settled in Brooklyn during the Dutch, then English, colonial period. Members of the Wyckoff family are all descended from Pieter Claesen Wyckoff, an influentual 17th century figure in New Amsterdam who established the Flatlands Dutch Reformed Church. After living near present day Albany, Claesen-Wyckoff and his wife, Grietje Van Ness-Wyckoff, settled on what is now the historic Wyckoff homestead in Flatlands, Brooklyn. While living on the Wyckoff homestead, Pieter Claesen Wyckoff became a landholder and justice of the peace. Claesen-Wyckoff and Van Ness-Wyckoff had eleven children who married other prominent families. The Wyckoff family tree is complex and spans the entire United States of America.
The Wyckoff House & Association, Inc. was formed in 1937 by descendants of Pieter Claesen Wyckoff and Grietje Van Ness-Wyckoff who came together to purchase the Pieter Claesen Wyckoff House. In the 1960s, the Wyckoff House Foundation gained ownership of the property and donated it to the New York City Department of Parks and Recreation. In 2001 the house was opened as a public museum offering school programs, public events, and community farmers markets. The Wyckoff House Museum perserves and educates the public from New York's oldest building through educational programs that connect people to the past.
Custodial History
The Wyckoff House papers were transferred to the Center for Brooklyn History on September 25, 2020. Prior to the transfer, the papers were housed at WHA in an unheated attic. WHA collected the papers from Wyckoff descendants on unknown dates.
Related Materials
Center for Brooklyn History holds the following related collections:
- Lefferts family papers (ARC.145)
- Jacques Cortelyou papers (ARC.025)
- Stoothoff family collection (ARC.150)
Scope and Contents
The Wyckoff House papers are mostly comprised of documents that range from 1670 to 1935 with the bulk of the collection spanning 1750 to 1870. The majority of the collection documents transactions and includes: enslaved people indentures and bills-of-sale, deeds, letters, maps, receipts, bonds, certificates, and other documents. While many of the documents do refer specifically to the Wyckoff family or the Pieter Claesen Wyckoff House, many of the papers document broader business dealings in the area that is currently Kings County, and mention many other Dutch or early colonists in the area, including some of the following families: Lott, Rapelje, Ryerson, Lefferts, Kowenhoven, Vanderbuilt, Schenck, and Vandeveer.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
If digital surrogates exist, they should be used in place of the originals whenever possible.
Dutch Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Bonds; Deeds; Receipts (financial records); Maps; Bills of sale; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- History -- 19th century; Marriage certificates; Passports; Birth certificates; Correspondence; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 19th century; Enslaved people -- bills of sale; Wyckoff House & Association
- Series I. Legal and Transactional Documents, 1687-1917; .75 Linear Feet in 1 half manuscript box and 1 16x20 OS box.
  Arrangement
  Documents in this series are grouped alphabetically by type, then arranged chronologically with folder or item level description.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains legal and transactional documents mostly created and collected by members of the Wyckoff family and their descendants from 1687 to 1917. The bulk of the material dates from the early 1700s to the mid 1800s and consists of deeds and bonds. Included in this series are four enslaved persons' bills-of-sale and one enslaved person's deed of indenture. In addition to deeds and bonds, there are bills-of-sale, certificates, wills, an oath of allegiance, pardon, passport, and receipts.
  - Deed of John Gibordson from Daniel Hendrickson for Land, March 13, 1700 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Deed of Indenture between Klaus Wyckoff and Cornelius Wyckoff for Land, 1714, 1715 (Box OS-42, Folder 2)
  - Deed of Cornelius Wyckoff from Wilhelmus Stoothoff for 25 Acres of Land in Flatlands, 1739, 1751 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Deed of Indenture between Abraham Wyckoff and Abraham and Sarah Rapelje for Land, May 23, 1800 (Box OS-42, Folder 2)
  - Deed of Indenture of Jack, an Enslaved Child, from Nicolas Schenk to Abraham Wyckoff, January 1, 1819 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Deeds, 1712-1897 (Box 1, Folder 1, Box 2, Folder 6, Folder 2)
  - Bill-of-sale of Sam, an Enslaved Child, from Nicolas and Peter Wyckoff to Abraham Wyckoff for 40 Pounds, May 18, 1801 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bill-of-sale of Lidge, an Enslaved Man, from Jarvis Whitman to Abraham Wyckoff for 225 Dollars, April 14, 1807 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bill-of-sale of David, an Enslaved Man, from Daniel Jones to George Lot for 132 Pounds, February 22, 1812 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bill-of-sale of Maria and Jack, Enslaved Mother and Son, from Ann Emmaus to Matthew Jones for 55 Pounds, October 4, 1813 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bills-of-sale, 1717-1838 (Box 1, Folder 6, Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Birth Certificate of Ida Aletta Wyckoff -- Photostatic Copy, June 2, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Bonds, 1689-1827 (Box 1, Folder 3, Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Census of Enslaved People in the Counties of Albany, 1755 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Contract, 1717 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Insurance Certificate, 1828-1829 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Marriage Certificate, 1868 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Mortgage Certificate, 1818 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Oath of Allegiance, 1687 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Pardon for Daniel Jones, Prisoner of War, August 15, 1778 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Passport, 1834 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Receipts, 1810-1835 (Box 1, Folder 11, Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Summons and Complaint, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Will of Pieter Wyckoff of Flatlands, New York, June 10, 1746 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Will of Abraham Emans of Gravesend, New York, January 11, 1777 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Will of Adam Boyse of Monmouth County, New Jersey, November 10, 1780 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Will of Peter Wyckoff of Hillsborough, New Jersey, May 25, 1813 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series II. Correspondence, Family Documents, and Notes, 1670-1888, undated; .20 Linear Feet in 1 20x24 OS box and 1 flat file folder.
  Documents in this series are grouped alphabetically by type, then arranged in chronological order with folder or item level description.
  This series contains documents and correspondence created and about members of the Wyckoff family dating from 1670 to 1888. The bulk of the material in this series is correspondence between members of the Wyckoff family dating from 1805 to 1869. Aside from the correspondence, there is a newspaper and certificate from the 1880s, and some documents from the early to mid 1800s with notes about the Wyckoff family.
  - Certificate of Service of Nicolas Wyckoff to the Williamsburg City Fire Insurance Company, August 10, 1883 (Folder 2)
  - Family Documents, 1670-1860, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Notes, 1690-1866, undated (Box 1, Folder 2, 17)
  - Letters and Envelope, 1805-1869, undated (Box 1, Folder 10, Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper, 1888 (Box OS-42, Folder 1)
- Series III. Maps, 1935; .05 Linear Feet in 1 flat file folder.
  Documents in this series are arranged chronologically at the folder level with item level description.
  This small series consists of two copies of a map which depicts a stretch of Old Kings Highway in Flatlands, Brooklyn. The map was drawn in 1935 by BDS Ryerson.
  - Maps of Old Kings Highway and Vicinity in the Town of Flatlands Neck, 1935 (Folder 1)